Okay, so let's talk about the probability
and impact matrix.
The probability in impact
matrix then is another
tool that you can use for
qualitative risk analysis.
Now, in qualitative, remember,
we are ranking our risk, right,
using arbitrary values.
And that's exactly the same thing that
we're doing here, right?
With the probability and impact matrix,
we would just use this matrix, right?
We're just going to use this matrix again
to come up with a relative ranking.
So here's a very simple example then of a
probability and impact matrix.
So there's two boxes.
The left-hand box is negative risk,
threats.
Right-hand box is showing opportunities,
right, positive risks.
So let's just look at one of them.
In this case, let's just look at threats,
right, this box here.
On the y-axis, you see probability.
On the x-axis here, we've got impact,
negative impact.
And you can see then, these numbers then
are basically percentages.
So there's a 5% impact, 10% impact,
20% impact, and then in the probability,
we've got 10%
probability, 30% probability,
50% probability, and so on and so forth.
Now these numbers are not going up
incrementally, because this isn't a graph.
This is just a table.
The numbers within
the table, then, just the
probability and impact
numbers multiplied together.
So, for example, 0.3 times 0.1 is 0.03.5
times 0.2 is 0.1.
It's just the two numbers multiply
together.
And then you could use these numbers here,
then, to, again, prioritize your risks.
Because, again, qualitative is all about
prioritizing your risks.
So this is a tool that you can use to
prioritize you.
risk.
So as a very simple example then,
let's say we've identified this risk,
risk A, wherever that risk is.
And we've identified that there's a
probability of 0.5, right?
So 50% probability of that risk occurring.
And if it occurs, the impact is going to
be 0.4.
So what's our risk score?
Right?
Well, 0.2.5 times 0.4, risk score is 0.2.
Let's say we've identified another risk,
risk B.
And the probability of that risk occurring
is high.
We give it a score of 0.7.
And the impact is very high.
We give it a score of 0.8.
So the risk score is then going to be
0.56.
0.7 times 0.8.56.
So which are the highest priority risk
here then?
Out of A and B, the highest
priority risk is going to naturally
be risk B because it's a much
higher risk score than risk A.
So any risk that you've identified that
fall within the dark shade will be a
higher priority than the risks that fall
within the light shade, there will be a
higher priority compared to the risks that
are in no shade.
All we're doing in qualitative risk
analysis is prioritizing your risk,
ranking your risk, but using these
arbitrary values.
And then one of the
tools you can use then is
this one called the
probability and impact matrix.
And this is just one very simple example.
This one is using percentages.
You could be using, again, high,
medium, low, high, very low, low,
medium high, medium,
medium, very high, you know, that
kind of classification for
what's probability and impact.
And so in the table here, you won't have
numbers.
Again, it'll just be high, medium low,
very high, very low, and so and so forth.
So there's many different ways,
again, we're just using arbitrary values.